A Guide to the Middlesex County (Va.) County Court Order Books and Index Cards to County Orders, 1673-1796 (bulk 1673-1726)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Middlesex County (Va.) County Court Order Books and Index Cards to County Orders, 1673-1796 (bulk 1673-1726)
The Library of Virginia
1048877-1127567 circa
1 box and 16 v.
Middlesex County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Middlesex County.
Historical Information
Middlesex County probably was named for the English county. It was formed from Lancaster County about 1669.
Numerous loose records from the nineteenth century including chancery, County Court Order Books and Index Cards to County Orders, and commonwealth causes are missing. Most volumes including deed books, will books, and order books exist because court clerk Philemon T. Woodward removed them from the courthouse for safekeeping during the Civil War.
Scope and Content
Middlesex County (Va.) County Court Order Books, 1673-1786 consist of 16 volumes of County Court Order Books. The County Court Order Books cover the years 1673-1726, 1745-1786. The Index Cards to County Orders are for Order Book entitled Orders, 1721-1726.
Order Books records all matters brought before the court when it was in session. It provides a synopses of cases in a neater, more organized form. These volumes are sometimes internally indexed; more rarely, there is a comprehensive index. A wide variety of information is found in this order book including: deeds, chancery causes, judgments, records of legal disputes heard before the county court and road orders.
In common law an (e)stray is a wandering animal whose owner is unknown. Records of strays are notices of discovery of lost livestock, with reports of commissioners appointed to determine proper reimbursment of the finder for caring for the animals. Middlesex included someone's lost boat in their list of strays.
Arrangement
Chronological
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Middlesex County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Middlesex County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Middlesex County Court Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localities Database found at the Library of Virginia web site.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Middlesex County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public Records -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.; Estray Records -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.; Inventories of descendants' estates -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.; Wills -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.; Fiduciary Accounting -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.; Deeds -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.
Geographical Names:
Middlesex County (Va.) -- History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Court Records-- Virginia -- Middlesex County.; Judicial records -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.; Local government records -- Virginia -- Middlesex County.
Contents List
- Order Book, 1673-1680
  Also known as Order Book, No. 1, [Deeds and Wills] 1673 - 1680. The book is arranged by groups of orders followed by copies of wills, deeds, bonds, etc mentioned in the orders.
- Order Book, 1680-1694
  Barcode Number 1127558 is Order Book, 1680-1694, Part 1, which contains pages 1-374. Barcode Number 1127558 is Order Book, 1680-1694, Part 2, which contains pages 375-728. This book is also known as Order Book Number 2.
- Order Book, 1694-1705
  Also known as Order Book, Number 3.
- Order Book, 1705-1710
  Also known as Order Book, Number 4.
- Order Book, 1710-1721
  Also known as Order Book Number 5.
- Orders, 1721-1726
  Also known as Order Book Number 6.
- Index Cards to County Orders, 1721-1726
  These cards index Order Book, Number 6, 1721-1726 which is not indexed.
- Orders, 1745-1752
  This order book was not given a number.
- Orders, 1752-1758
- Orders, 1758-1767
  Barcode Number 1127258 is Order Book, 1758-1767, Part 1, pages 1-500, which contain Orders 1758-1765. Barcode Number 1127259 is Order Book, 1758-1767, Part 2 ,pages 520-647, which contain Orders October 1, 1765-1767. This book also contains a second pagination of pages 1-68 which contains Wills, Inventories, etc, 1794 - 1795. This book also contain a third pagination, of which pages 1-6 [1] which contain List of Estrays, 1773-1782, undated, and on page 5 there is a list of two Bills of Exchange recorded on 23 February 1778.
- Order Book, 1769-1772
- Order Book, 1772-1782
- Orders, 1783-1784
  This book begins with an Index of the Orders and is followed by pages 1-60 that contain Orders 1783-1784. The second pagination begins with an Index of the Deeds and is followed by pages 1-218 that contain Deeds 1785-1791. The third pagination, pages 1-69 contains Executions 1769-1772.
- Orders, 1784-1786
  This Order Book was not given a number.